"Risks and Benefits of Red and Green Rooibos Tea"
Black, green, and white teas
are all made
from the same evergreen plant.
Herbal tea, on the other hand,
involves pouring water
over any plant in the world
other than the tea plant.
In my book How Not to Age,
I covered hibiscus
and chamomile tea
in my chapters on boosting AMPK
and blocking inflammation.
Are there any other
notable herbal teas
that may have
anti-aging properties?
Rooibos, also known as red tea,
is a caffeine-free herbal tea
grown in a mountainous region
of South Africa.
It has been shown to increase
the lifespan of C. elegans
by as much as 23 percent
under conditions
of oxidative stress,
presumed to be due
to its antioxidant properties.
In a head-to-head comparison
of fifteen herbal teas,
rooibos came in at number two
(after dandelion)
for in vitro
antioxidant power.
Green rooibos—
analogous to green tea—
worked better
in the C. elegans study
than red rooibos,
which is the commercially
more common oxidized form
(akin to black tea).
Green rooibos tea has about
twice the antioxidant capacity
compared to red,
though both similarly increase
the blood antioxidant capacity
after consumption.
Within six weeks,
rooibos intake can decrease
markers of oxidative damage
and even drop LDL cholesterol
by nearly 27 points (mg/dl)
compared to control,
but the dose used
(six cups (1440 ml) a day)
is more than most people drink.
No smaller quantity
has apparently yet been
put to the test.
If you want to try it at home,
though the "optimal cup"
is said to require
10 minutes of steeping,
it appears extraction plateaus
at five minutes;
so, more time
doesn't seem necessary.
The traditional
method of brewing
is to simmer the rooibos,
which does appear to improve
its antioxidant capacities
compared to
hot or cold steeping.
The practice fell into disfavor
with the advent of tea bags
for convenience in the 1960s.
The same bag transition
happened to black tea—
jumping from 5 percent
in 1960 in the U.K.
to more than 95 percent
by 2007—
but that switch
may have actually had
favorable consequences.
Because the tea in bags tends
to be chopped so much finer
than loose tea,
the extra surface area
improves the extraction.
It only takes two minutes
of infusion time
to extract the same quantity
of tea compounds
from bagged black tea
that it would take
ten minutes to extract
from loose leaf black tea.
Ideally, we should steep for
more than two minutes, though.
Flavonoid extraction
from black tea isn't complete
until about minute four.
Green tea maybe brewed
for three minutes
at 85 degrees C, Celsius
(for both optimum
nutrition and taste)
and white tea
at 98C for seven minutes.
(White tea brewed from bags
also results in almost twice
the antioxidant capacity
of loose leaf.)
Rooibos has
an excellent safety record,
though there have been
four cases reported
in the medical literature
of liver toxicity
associated with rooibos use,
the most convincing of which
involved two separate
hospitalizations
for acute hepatitis
following a resumption
of rooibos consumption.
All cases resolved
without incident
once the patients stopped
drinking rooibos,
but as with any new tea,
herb, supplement, or drug,
immediately consult
your healthcare practitioner
if you develop
symptoms of liver trouble,
such as abdominal pain,
dark urine, or jaundice
(which is yellowing
of the skin or eyes).
One nice bonus to rooibos is
that it's effectively fair trade
by definition.
Starting in 1993, nearly
every country on the planet
ratified the Convention
on Biological Diversity,
a breakthrough in global
environmental policymaking
that aimed
to conserve biodiversity
by rewarding Earth's custodians
with fair and equitable
benefit sharing.
And the rooibos
benefit sharing agreement
was the first
industry-wide agreement
to be formed
with indigenous peoples
in accordance
with the Convention.